so um one of the wonderful things about
the hyack conference is uh a few years
ago a group of women working in the
field got together and said you know
this is this isn't great there's only a
few of us in in search there's only a
few of us in it generally what can we do
about that and we're only a very small
corner of the IT world uh but I think
the women of Search Group has had had a
huge impact act in
encouraging uh coaching supporting women
working in this field and promoting
their achievements so I'm very pleased
today that in our our regular women of
search slot um Ella is going to uh talk
about the life of a search system and
this is a a a presentation that's been
compiled by the women of Search Group
and Ella is to deliberate on there beh
but she has a group of very talented
women uh behind there as well so uh Ella
is a software developer who accidentally
entered search about nine years ago and
stayed there to all of our benefit and
she's uh she's polish she lives in C and
um she is an independent search
consultant but please put your hands
together for the women of search L
hello first uh thank you all for being
here and thank for all the great talks
we have had heard so far um my name is
Ella as you heard and I will present a
collective work from woman of search and
I will really be reading a lot of slides
because that makes me feel confident so
a word of introduction we all present
here are are already in the search
domain our expertise and experience vary
but we are not new to the topic many
Engineers companies and agencies are in
their early stages and we hope this
presentation will provide some
historical explanation guidance and
perspective on the evolution of search
system
it
move
yes so let's uh let us properly
introduce ourselves however our name
woman of search pretty much removes the
mystery the implementational details are
as follow we were founded three years
ago in May 2021 we have two branches EU
and us actually this picture is from our
us colleagues um our community is 257
members strong and and I had to update
this slide many times because every day
someone new is joining we are a Vibrant
Community dedicated to empowering
celebrating woman in Search and related
Tech fields we try to provide a platform
for networking mentorship and knowledge
sharing here is our slack Channel Please
join if you would like to you don't need
to be a woman just you want to be part
please join you're
welcome whenever possible we take
pictures we have many pictures one of
them I think this is from the last year
or two years ago I stopped
tracking more pictures and some updates
about us uh there is a happy hour Group
which continues on the very first
Wednesday of each month at 900 a.m. PT
totally voluntary we talk about anything
anything literally and there is a
typescript working group founded and led
by Moon Lim from South Korea time zone
is a bit challenging but we made
it so let's zoom in on our talk
pick and
picture uh the big idea it is an analogy
that came to our minds during a
brainstorming so what it is uh a believe
a search system is like a living
organism it starts simple and can't
escape inevit inevitable Evolution the
only challenge is that fast-paced
mutation gives a rise to chaos and
complexity the options are extensive
um a word about the evolution of search
in a chronical way uh
pre uh during the last 24 years many
things have changed in our
industry um I won't say that pre-2000
was a prehistoric era but we have come a
long way some of the most important
Milestones are marked on the timeline so
pre 2000 we were focused on pattern
search and exact search then 2,000 text
analysis 2010 natural language
processing of course there are just you
know ballpack numbers don't keep us
fixed on the exact dates multi-word
synonyms in 2011 personalization big
thing of
2014 named entity recognition
2015 then learning to rank in
178 all about semantic search and since
2022 till now we are in in multimodal
multilingual model assisted search and
we stayed here as of now since 2011 we
enter the era of datadriven
factors quick
agenda first we will look into searching
a grand scheme of things then how things
usually evolve some adjustments to
improve the state of things then up
leveling and few advices from
us this is a very abstract model of a
search search in a grand scheme of
things on the left we have a data on the
right there is a search need the middle
component is a big unknown for now
firstly you ask yourself a question what
should I do and then you start
researching on the topic and may get the
impression this is a scary word but
actually there is nothing to
fear so what's so
hard it's a complexity hidden in
multidisciplinary tasks building search
is not linear
it isn't let's look at some Concepts
topics questions and concerns involved
in building search
system so what's so hard about the data
a quick look into hovering topics and
just please remember this is not a
complete list is to give you an idea why
it's so complex so what do we have here
structure or unstructured data or both
what is in general type of a data and
then how do you provide qu quality
assurance
do you pre-process the data what about
normalization business rules pruning
then what data should we even
use how to extract relevant signals from
the data we have already moreover how to
generate new
signals big question of data volume how
much data is
there do we store and how do we store
and access the data how to handle data
data corruption what about data security
and gdpr next how handle data
recovery how new does data need to be
what about the freshness how should we
process it on the batch on schedule or
we need to support live updates do we
track the data version how to bring data
into searchable format and lastly new
emerging concept data machine
learning let's move on what does the
black Bo box magic entails firstly
remember that we build systems for
humans can I explain it to the others do
I even understand my system and can I
override
it probably one of the biggest questions
what is my vision and my strategy in the
search retriever ranking Concepts
business factors user tracking
signals what is my competitive Advantage
with my
search which type of search do you
need keyword
Vector hybrid image voice and so many
more not listed here big bucket of ab
tests offline lab search metrics and
everlasting
kpis lastly but not last how to build
self-learning system and how to build
robust and performance
system next version of things to keep in
mind here for just search please
how should we explain results to user
how should we explain hidden query
changes that happen behind the scenes
what about refining the results and how
even reenable enable refinements to the
user UI and ux concerns huge topic
presenting the results how to guide the
user on the
journey and since we are about the user
his satisfaction implicit feedback
explicit feedback tracking and tracking
feedback sorry and
personalization performance and
scalability scalability ab testability
multil language platform multiplatform
support and ever living kpis on this
level
too so in the beginning you are just
here you have a data store bunch of
unstructured data structured documents
images audio files streaming data and
prob much much
more but you want to get here you want
to have a secure Fancy Search system
fancy index pay index pipelines low
latency beautiful UI and happy user at
the end how to get
there okay firstly we begin with a
typical story of building a search
system let's see things are rolling when
you are new to the topic this is a
little of a storytelling part and I'll
be reading a lot of notes for easier for
me and I don't want to ruin a f for you
so
prepare how it usually
starts first you take your data and push
them somehow to the search engine of
your choice probably if an off in an
offline batch mode on demand or on a
schedule then you build some backend
search Logic and expose it via search
API to qu data the next step is building
a fancy or rudimental UI soon enough you
will notice that data processing become
a bottleneck volume grows and becomes so
enormous that it pushes you into
constant right operation mode so you'll
scale up and scale out the entire
platform the money counter is
sticking product requirements force you
to switch from offline processing to
online so you build a new data
processing platform that adds even more
right pressure the money counter goes up
you realize that probably not all the
changes should trigger an update and not
all of them are equally important so you
add checks Delta checks and priority
Concepts somewhere during that process
you notice that data quality is not what
you expected you invest in data
enrichment and data augmentation the
focus is on adding more signals to
existing data the more the better right
the AI and all the big guns are pulled
out the money counter doubles its speed
finally the data quality becomes a Hot
Topic in your team content sanitization
and the duplication are implemented
sadly only now and someday there is a
Doomsday the search engine crashes on
you and you lose your data the search
engine was an authoritative source of
Truth there were no recent backups and
re the data the whole Pipeline on Source
takes 3 days not a good
situation conc currently the quality of
search results bothers you all along the
simple user tracking tool you put in
place for measuring kpis shows low CTR
low success metric or low engagement you
can point finger some obvious problems
with
results tempted with an easy fix you
apply the Band-Aid into search API or
directly into search engine query but
that does not scale and you know it so
you start collecting underperforming
queries in a spreadsheet there are too
many to keep fixing them in the code
base independently the outcome is hard
to predict so your approach evolves you
build your own or use existing tool to
manage your queries and override or tune
the systems default Behavior this can
quickly get out of control and you end
up with two parallel search systems back
office system and default search that
may override each
other following Trends and mainstream
media you are temped to incorporate new
technologies you integrate with AI
Services hoping for better query
understanding query enrichment
classification you build them yourself
in a more risky approach instead of
using Integrations anyway spending money
gets to the next level the desperation
level achieves a new all-time high
despite all that time and effort the
return on investment stays low however
spending money gets insanely High you
start realizing that the changes you
need are more fundamental and Technology
dependent intrigued or forced you start
exploring how the search engine of your
choice Works actually and how to operate
and tune it you discover a variety of
search functions and their
usage at some point you read that
pushing data efficiently into search
engine is
insufficient it needs proper modeling
AKA design for search and here
congratulations you have started
connecting the dots and experimenting
with different mappings and search
Logic your time investment results in
your very first search strategy it could
be a greedy algorithm with small boosts
on specific fields or a multi-stage
pipeline it doesn't matter if you are
proud of it as it clearly fixes the
problems at hand full of hope you deploy
it to production waiting for a big
breakthrough which doesn't happen and
instead you have unwanted side effects
finally you get trapped in a cycle of
failing attempts our story continues on
another slide this is a long journey
always after a few dozen of attempts you
notice a gap between your test and test
queries and production to be more
successful you are missing your actual
users queries so you invest in building
a query log if you are lucky queries
from production are close enough to the
one you tuned for if not you need to
start again with your improvements you
learn that's an iterative process after
a few iterations like that you probably
suffer from long Cycles your goal now is
to confirm progress or at least prevent
regression quickly so you invest in a
better test environment when your ideas
can be validated quickly before they hit
production what is missing here that's
the validation set against which you can
predict better out outcomes of your
improvements and some way of measur
quantify the change luckily you quickly
realize that data is already available
that's the user tracking you have for
kpis probably some important details are
missing in that data for example filter
usage return document IDs or sequence of
actions are not combined into a session
but after some adaptations you can
finally incorporate that crucial data
into your offline labor atory other
essential components of this lab golden
set of queries and judgment lists all
those mechanics make you faster but not
necessarily more successful something is
missing here the attention now lies on
the last piece untouched so far the UI
what you do here is patch things out to
connect users to the results you want
them to have lastly you just remove the
sort by relevance option
no I hope you liked it let's take a look
at possible adjustments to what we have
seen um where you can apply a few
adjustments just to improve the state
not dramatically change it but improve
it our story
continues introducing a data
warehouse centralize all inflight
processes and focus on producing a
custodial data warehouse what are the
benefits of
it own data flowing through your system
and whoever owns a clean data Masters
the world if you are not building a lock
Search application that matters to
you it's an authoritative source of true
changes are being track tracked you know
who changed it what changed it and when
it
happened standardized data with unified
quality do you feel like indexing the
same information multiple times from
different sources and each one has a
different quality this can be your
answer
control rate and throughput of your
rights don't be reactive
only costly operations are performed
only once on the standardized
data as you can see we have a six
adjustments this is the second one truck
Tru user
Journey undeniably this is a very high
effort with very high return on
investments this should be one of your
early
Investments TR track users before and
after their search sessions join events
in a search session it is very hard to
reason from registry of back of
events use data to understand users and
their problems and to prioritize
fixes Define universal schema for events
I think we heard about it it's important
use for personalization and ml
tasks use that data to measure offline
relevance
and finally break cycle of isolated
improvements and broadside effects don't
work in silos
syis adjustments into building a testing
Frameworks um we have to Frameworks for
offline and online
experimentations you should build both
of them or at least one high effort with
high return on investments also create
golden set of queries to measure a gain
for e-commerce those can be iPhone
queries never breaker iPhone queries for
conversational system those can be
something like hatred speech G guard
rails
Sor yes manual data set labeling still
matters standardized analysis for easier
comparison of experiments
results choose the right offline metric
or metrics and very important monitor
alignment between offline and online
metrics because if they get out of Sy
something is definitely
wrong adjustments into manual coration
sorry give may be a little disturbing
but it's just there for a second
occasionally override the default
behavior of your system we will we all
would like to have this
option however use it sparingly it's
just a temporary fix you don't want it
to overshadow your actual search
system it is most useful when users
exhibit brand new search
behavior and also useful in specialized
domains like medical fields for
example and it can really save your day
sometime search
strategy at some point split retrieval
from the whole search strategy it is the
first sequential stream it can be a
multi-stage
process documents designed for search
needs to support your search strategy
model your data as you will be searching
in
it have a fallback when the fancy things
needs emergency shutdown because
sometimes they
do U monitor your latency
always and the
last our proposals to ranking strategy
improvements speed ranking it is the
second sequential stream it can be a
multi-stage and multi-objective process
rate candidates based on business values
and quality checks
first sometimes it is a game changer not
the retrieval
phase apply your own personalization
data points are in the search tracking
before you try to reach out for third
party
Services learning to rank is great try
first with offline approach before going
online which is most costly more costly
operational
so having all that level up where when
are you ready to level up your search
bring it to the next
level when should you reach for more
part first do you and this is a
questioner do you have lots of un
data pretty good end to end search
system in place
already enough Engineers to Green Field
a new project
sizable budget for Vector search
databases and
llms if all your answers are yes then
you might be ready for Gen how can you
use it at your advantage and reach your
existing res search results with
semantic results build a rack chat
interface include rack based signals
into learning to rank generate did you
mean candidates augment spell check and
generate keywords metadata just
examples
proposal also questioner do you have lot
have data with inherent hierarchical
relationships like e-commerce categories
or specialized
vocabularies is your data relationship
based like a social
networks do you have Specialists that
can help with the information science
aspects if your answers are yes
then you might be ready for building to
build a Knowledge Graph use it to
disambiguate user intent and increase
recall by pulling overarching
Concepts yeah I'm pretty fast Our
advice introducing need driven
development
ndd build what you need as you need it
no sooner no later
start small and simple pick the easiest
tool for the job to get you started now
try to max out your technology before
you ditch to something else technology
is just a medium towards your goal there
are no really greater search engines A
or B it's just pick whatever get you
started right
now read research exercise on questions
and options do your due diligence no one
will do it for you
do and
Don remember measure something anything
that you can Benchmark against don't do
things to just sound cool use things
that work for you limit entropy of your
technology stack establish good practice
for working with data and then
extrapolate don't don't take shortcuts
on data it won't pay off don't overstate
impact of the new technology
but don't be
ignorant don't build rigid system search
is not a
colosium remember need driven
development thank
you
wonderful thank you Ella and and extra
points for you know delivering a deck
that's been built by a group of people
is never an easy thing to do uh
and that's also one of those one of
those decks if I could show that to
pretty much all my customers at the very
beginning and get them of it that would
be a very lovely thing to be honest
there's some really good Baseline and
solid adise there so we've got a um
we've got a question from online to kick
us off uh some ask uh what does it mean
by split retrieval and split ranking do
you mean
organizationally um maybe if you have
resources but when you are new into
technology when you start you just put
everything into one bucket and hoping
will work some somehow and then you even
may not realize that there are actually
two concepts how you retrieve and how
you rank so if you want to be more
specialized you can split organ
organizationally or even like do it
iteratively still within the elastic
search but please keep in mind that
there are two separate separate
streams great thank you so do we have
any questions from the
room yes
thanks for the great talk uh have you
had experience with uh clients or uh out
there in the real world with Knowledge
Graph learning and actually serving it
alongside your search NCS and uh you
know uh I I think that it can really
help with query understanding but maybe
uh a more
practical um story might help cool yes
and no so explicitly on that slides
worked our friend uh audre so I will
happily take this question and she'll
get back to you answers I will note your
U not your email or um LinkedIn
profile you're not ah cool
um what I experienc with knowledge
graphs it's for e-commerce and it was
really for just traversing the graph to
get the better attributes for the
products that is my limited experience
with knowledge graphs still very useful
for e-commerce that's how we used it
great thank you um any other questions
sure sure
mat I mean I've seen that um especially
for the uh query understanding or query
U I would say interpretation so you
would need like expli explicit uh you
know kind of hierarchical you know way
how each query decomposes and I think
this is very useful in uh for example
with medicine and finance and also
Insurance domains so I feel like uh
people usually feel like uh tempted to
try things out as as Ella has
beautifully you know also captured on
the slides so I think the whole idea was
that you know things that were domains
might not be applicable like there are
no uh rule of thumbs so try it out at
the smaller scale and then scale up I
think that was probably the
idea great um so somebody on online has
asked um great said great slides will
you share of course all the slides from
all the talks will be shared on the
hastac website anyone who's bought a
ticket will get Early Access and then
we'll share them all publicly in a few
weeks any further questions
yes yeah hi thank you for the great talk
uh I was thinking it would
be say maturity maybe in my organization
and the system which would say okay
you're here and then you know you could
do this to I don't know go to some let's
say better you know those would be out
of those six steps you know which could
which could be the most impactful one so
just I don't know I think this would be
possible I promise we'll make those
changes and it will be included in the
presentation good feedback uh a minor
plug for open source connections this
exactly what we do with a lot of clients
true we we have a maturity Matrix which
covers a lot of those things so sorry to
to jump in on that one
would remiss of me not to mention it um
do we have any other questions
yeah thanks for the excellent talk on
the uh sort of data quality part uh do
you maybe have any practical experience
from one of your clients uh one of the
clients of your colleagues that about
the data quality part so we're for
example in a situation where the search
engine part is kind of up and running
but a lot of the it's not necessarily
unstructured data but it's maybe
unlabeled or doesn't really have all the
features and filters that we'd like to
have but it's hard for us to convince
our stakeholders and our internal
customers to spend the probably copious
amounts of times correctly labeling it
because the search is quite bad but then
the search can't improve because they're
not really labeling the data so we're
kind of stuck in this uh catch22 have
you encountered similar situations and
if so how would we fix that uh
just to be sure you're referencing the
data labeling right okay it's very hard
like no none of the clients would like
to pay it if you can see it on the UI
obviously it's like considered to be low
level investment we know it's important
to have it luckily I have been working
with a POS that understand this uh
importance and they were like helping
course uh to convince the CL clients
that this is really worth for investment
if you cannot it cannot have it easily
there are companies who can do
it substantially with a lower cost than
within the organizational is a different
topic like if they can do it right um I
would say try to synthesize you know the
the data set you have try to take
another approach think about the queries
we heard about this concept also uh in
this conference queries that you can use
to um describe the search results you
would like to have and then use those
queries as a labels but also it depends
on what that theb you like to have if
they are label in type of categories uh
queries sorry that may help you but if
it's like data quality 1 2 3 four five
then drive it from the quality checks
from the ingesting pipeline for
example um just to add to that and I
think this is the the classic garbage in
garbage out problem and it applies to
search it applies to AI it applies to
all of these things and we know this
um one of the things is to educate the
people dealing with data in what search
needs you know why do you need to clean
your data up explain how a search engine
works they might understand it a bit
better sorry sometimes what also helps
is like small PC on the side like take
just the subset of data Master them
clean it and show like really I didn't
change how search works I just worked on
the data and I did it for 100 documents
you see the results are already
better learn by example
any other
questions excellent talk thank you so
along the life of a search system how
are the usually organizations shaping in
like when the search team is being
created when the search team is being
grown when the search team is being
split when the Consultants are brought
in could you share a bit on on that
thank
you I think it may be Revenue driven the
some companies are really about the
search and they take money out of a
search that's how the revenue stream is
provided and then they they usually will
have understanding that the search is
important and we need to have investment
in there but for some companies search
is just a Sidetrack like addition to
something and then it's much complex
because internally you have many
contradictory um signals from CEO from
account thing that it's actually a side
hustle we should not invest into
that the money always talks and convince
the people if not then I would take the
users Community if they start
complaining a lot and someone will hear
that the search results are not good
enough maybe someone else has a
different opinion okay um so we've got a
a question online Sam um says I work for
a Marketplace where items are unique and
a sale removes it from the search
engine any tips for obtaining judgment
lists or golden query sets with such a
use case so you maybe using some kind of
historic snapshot or how how would you
put together a set of golden queries
when some of the documents are just
going to
disappear it's a great
question very popular in the
marketplaces as pointed out
um then it's not really judgment list
for this particular product if it can be
as high volatility gets in or gets out
it's more about that clustering of very
similar products there is a benefit
hidden like if you have one particular
product that is very rare you probably
have another one which are equally rare
don't get fixed into this one specific
product it doesn't matter extrapolate
find another cluster of similar products
and address the topic at once do not
work in sylosis from snapshots yes but
that's a whole pipeline like to
clustering
products okay great thank you hope that
aners your question Sam um any other
questions from the
room okay we've got one more uh online
uh de BR says uh you said human judgment
labels play an important role but as we
know it's very expensive to generate
those what about employing Advanced
semi-supervised labeling approaches know
more machine learning driven would that
work
yes I have no experience with that but
um may work I would say don't be
ignorant so I'm really open to that
suggestions however someone before had
manually labeled that some data that's
why now you have the machine learning
automated solution so it's
unavoidable great thank you so do we
have any more
questions right so we've got a little
time now and I'm I'm going to we're
going to widen the discussion a little
bit but firstly please thank Ella again
thank you